Finding Aid for Tom Downs papers, 1947-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Tom Downs papers 1947-2007
Downs, Tom, 1916-
851142 Aa 2
Legal advisor to the Michigan A.F.L.-C.I.O. and the Democratic State Central Committee; vice chairman of the Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962; and member of the Michigan Employment Security Commission, 1949-1965. Correspondence, minutes, reports and newspaper clippings concerning the administrations of Michigan governors G. Mennen Williams and John B. Swainson, the problems of employment and unemployment, and the recount of the 1962 gubernatorial election in Minnesota won by Karl Rolvaag.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
19 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
The collection was the gift of Tom Downs (donor no. 3857 ) and came to the library beginning in 1961.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Tom Downs was born July 11, 1916 in Spokane, Washington. He earned both his undergraduate and law degrees at the University of Michigan. During the 1937 Flint sit down strike against General Motors he worked with Victor Reuther and the UAW strikers. He would eventually serve as counsel for the Michigan State AFL-CIO, working with its president, Gus Scholle.
Tom Downs served as a Commissioner of the Michigan Employment Security Commission (MESC) during the G. Mennen Williams era, transforming an agency representing employers' interests to one representing employees' interests. He was one of three vice presidents of the 1961-1962 Michigan Constitutional Convention. Although the Democrats did not have a majority of the delegates, they greatly affected the ultimate 1963 Constitution. In 1982, he was a part of a successful bi-partisan effort to prevent Michigan from adopting the death penalty. He served on the Grand Valley College Board of Control, the American Lung Association of Michigan, the National Council of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws, the Michigan Law Revision Commission, the Michigan Political History Society, the Michigan Council for the Arts, and as an adjunct professor at the Thomas M. Cooley Law School. He died in 2007.
The Tom Downs collection includes correspondence, minutes, reports and newspaper clippings concerning the administrations of Michigan governors G. Mennen Williams and John B. Swainson, the problems of employment and unemployment, and the recount of the 1962 gubernatorial election in Minnesota won by Karl Rolvaag. The collection is organized in the following series: Political and other activities, 1949-1965; Michigan Employment Security Commission; Michigan Constitutional Convention and related; Miscellaneous; Sound Recordings; Visual Materials; Oral history project, 1995; and Writings, research, and later activities.
Subjects:
AFL-CIO.; Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Labor unions--Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan Employment Security Commission.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Minnesota.; Rolvaag, Karl F., 1913-1990; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Unemployed--Michigan.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Politics and government.; Downs, Tom, 1916-
Contributors:
Bluestone, Irving.; Fraser, Douglas A. (Douglas Andrew), 1916-2008.; Hart, Adelaide, 1900-
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Political and other activities 1949-1965
  - 1949-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-November 1961 (Box 2)
  - December 1961-May 1962 (Box 3)
  - June 1962-April 1963 (Box 4)
  - May 1963-November 1963 (Box 5)
  - December 1963-May 1965 (Box 6)
  - Minnesota Gubernatorial Election Recount file 1962 (Box 6)
- Michigan Employment Security Commission
  - Minutes 1956-May 1959 (Box 7)
  - Minutes June 1959-1961 (Box 8)
  - Minutes 1962-1963 (Box 9)
  - Minutes 1964-1965 (Box 10)
  - Legislation file 1962-1964 (Box 10)
- Michigan Constitutional Convention and related
  - Working papers 1961-1963 (Box 11)
  - Working papers 1961-1963 (Box 12)
    (continued)
  - Working papers 1961-1963 (Box 13)
  - Michigan Constitution recount vote files 1963 (Box 14)
  - Reapportionment suit 1963 (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous
  - Democratic State Central Committee legal advisor files 1955 (Box 15)
  - Job training files (Box 15)
  - Michigan Employment Security Commission publications (Box 15)
  - Miscellanea (Box 15)
- Sound recordings, 5" and 7" recording tapes
  - Constitutional Convention tapes 1961-1962, 5 tapes (Box 16)
  - Ratification campaign against the new proposed constitution 1963, 16 reels (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous cassettes, 32 audiocassettes in 2 cassette boxes (Box 17)
    (many of the cassettes concern Judge Miles Lord and the Minnesota Reserve mining case)
- Visual materials
  - Miscellaneous photographs of Con-Con delegates 1962 (Box 17)
    (include informal snapshots)
  - Michigan Con-Con 40th Anniversary Commemoration Events, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 17)
  - Toast and Tribute to Tom Downs November 12, 1996, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 17)
    (see also oversize folder)
    (include TD with Victor Reuther, Gus Scholle, Stephen Nisbet, Jennifer Granholm, Edward Hutchinson)
  - Volume of editorial cartoons drawn by Bill Day of the Detroit Free Press, 1993-1994 (Volume 1)
- Oral history project 1995
  - Interviews conducted by TD (Box 18)
    (each contains VHS tape, sound cassette, and transcription except for Jeffrey which includes VHS tape only)
    - Douglas Fraser (Box 18)
    - Irving Bluestone (Box 18)
    - Adelaide Hart (Box 18)
    - Mildred Jeffrey (Box 18)
  - Interview of TD August 1995 conducted by Bob LaBrant for the Michigan Political History Society, 1 videotapes VHS (TM); 1 audiocassettes; 1 transcriptions (Box 18)
  - Interview of TD March 30, 1995 conducted by Sidney Fine, 2 audiocassettes (Box 18)
    (includes transcription and related material)
  - Oral Interviews-Miscellaneous (Box 18)
- Writings, research, and later activities
  - 90th Birthday Party 2006 (Box 18)
  - Abraham Lincoln and the Second Revolution 2001 (Box 18)
  - Articles, Newsclippings (Box 18)
  - Articles, Newsclippings, Photos (Box 18)
  - Awards (Box 18)
  - Board of State Canvassers (Box 18)
  - Brennan Center for Justice (Box 18)
  - Briefs (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Democratic Party, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Electoral College (Box 19)
  - FestEve 1996 (Box 19)
    (organization established to celebrate alcohol-free New Years celebration)
  - Gubernatorial Inauguration (Box 19)
  - How to Pick a Doctor, by Tom Downs (Box 19)
  - Judicial Assistant (Box 19)
  - LaRouche, Lyndon (Box 19)
  - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 19)
  - Medical Malpractice (Box 19)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention, 2 folders (Box 19)
    (mainly reunion materials)
  - Michigan Employment Security Commission (MESC) & Remembrances (Box 19)
  - Michigan Leadership Institute, Bylaws, Sept 20 1995 (Box 19)
  - Michigan Political History News (with articles about Tom Downs (Box 19)
  - Michigan Political History Society (Box 19)
  - Michigan Works Progress Administration annual report 1942 (Box 19)
  - Now It Can Be Told (Gus Scholle, the Michigan CIO, and the state Democratic Party) (Box 19)
  - Obituary and Memorial (Box 19)
  - Out of the Box (Box 19)
  - Petition, Primer (Box 19)
  - Programs (Box 19)
  - Public Service Commission (Box 19)
  - Resume (Box 19)
  - Scholle, Gus (relation to Democratic Party and support of apportionment) (Box 19)
  - Student's Workers Federation (Box 19)
  - Supreme Court, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Thanksgiving Political Fun Fest (Box 19)
  - Thomas M. Cooley Law School -- Election Law (Box 19)
  - Toast & Tribute 1996 (Box 19)
  - Tobacco (Box 19)
  - UAW Democratic Party (Box 19)
  - Walter P. Reuther Library Research (Box 19)
  - Writings (Box 19)
  - Citations, tributes, etc. (Folder 1)